In the previous lesson, we were introduced
to
fluids and we learned about fluid
mechanics
and how it was separated into both fluid
dynamics
and fluid dynamics.
One thing I want to mention about last
video
that I forgot to mention is that the units
for
density are in kilograms.
Oops. They are in kilograms per
metres cubed.
Or kilograms per metres cubed.
Or if you're doing chemistry, which some
of
you might also be taking, it would be in
kilograms
because chemistry, usually you would use
grams
per decimetres cubed.
Or grams per litre would also work because
a
decimetre cubed is also a litre. But we
will
be using kilograms per metre cubed.
And pressure, they are measured in either
kilopascals
or atoms. PA, or, and
this is just basically, what this is, is
it's
the atmospheric pressure at sea level is
one
atom. And kilopascals are another unit.
101, I believe, kilopascals is equal to
one
atmospheric pressure. And
for IB, another good thing to know,
especially
for chemistry, is there are certain
conditions
where you will be doing your calculations.
This is standard temperature pressure
conditions.
And I'm telling you this because it's
pretty
useful to know ahead of time. Especially
if
you're like grade 9 or 10 and you haven't
been
introduced to the chemistry. So standard
temperature
pressure conditions are basically a set
unit
of conditions that you often use to make
your
calculations. And what this is, is
pressure
is equal to 100 kilopascals.
Or if you're doing AP, it would be one
atmospheric
pressure. And temperature is zero degrees
Celsius,
or you could say 273.15 Kelvin if you
like.
And yeah, basically these are a set of
conditions
that are really useful to know ahead of
time.
Because you're going to have to use it
anyways
if you're going into IB, whether it's
physics
or chem, or maybe even mainstream as well.
Anyways, today's lesson we are going to be
starting
buoyancy.
So if you've ever tried to push in a
beach,
let's say a beach ball underwater, or it
would
start going up. Or if you swim, if you try
to
push one of those paddle boards or a pool
buddy
up, it would also go up.
And this is governed by buoyancy.
Anything below a liquid would have
buoyancy,
buoyant force. Or if you would say it more
scientifically
and you will learn later, anything that
displaces
volume from a liquid and has density would
have
a buoyant force acting on it.
Um, yeah.
So, first of all, why do some things
sink? And why do some things float?
Well, as you have learned, hopefully
learned
before, for a free-body diagram, usually
let's
say you have a rock, there are two forces
governing
the motion of the rock. In this case, the
gravitational
force and the buoyant force.
Let's just call it FB. If the net force is
pointing
down, if the gravitation, the magnitude of
the
gravitational force is bigger than the
magnitude
of the buoyant force, then it's going to
sink.
So we know that F net equals FB minus FG.
If this is bigger and this is smaller,
then
this ball is going to sink. And if it's
the
other way around, if the buoyant force is
larger
and the gravitational force is smaller,
then
it's going to float. And what are the
key determinants of buoyancy?
Well, the buoyant force depends entirely
on
only two things. The density of the
liquid,
of the fluid, and the volume, the
volume of the object that's submerged, or
the
volume displaced. And the buoyant force
equation is the density of the fluid times
gravity, times, or the acceleration of
gravity,
times the volume displaced.
And this
can be used to basically calculate it.
So let's say if you have a ball underwater
and
the ball, you want to calculate whether it
sinks
or not. Let's say the ball has a radius of
five.
Let's make this bigger. Let's say the ball
has
a radius of five metres, or a
sphere, let's say. Then the area would be
five
over two times five metres cubed.
Times pi, sorry. And whatever you get
would
be your volume displaced.